welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right check-ins I feel calm and
stoic so welcome to the stoah I'm Peter
Lindbergh the steward of the stoah and
the Stowe is a place for us to cohere in
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge of this moment and before I
introduce today's guests just give me
maybe give Eric and whoever's new here
so an idea of what the stoic actually is
at this point I don't know I don't know
how to even describe it but sort of this
online digital campfire that's of
organically emerged that has a couple
components to it one of them being a
wisdom gym where we have a lot of cool
events regular sessions with John Rafi
he calls an ecology of practices
practices where we can actually practice
wisdom and then we have other ones like
sense making series where I invite
people who have our epistemic
authorities in certain areas and kind of
Q&A is like this and there's sort of
like a community village forming here
and the idea here is that we want to
move away from mimetic tribes to embody
tribes because beauty is found in
communitas so that's a little esoteric
101 for what the stone is about and
today we have Eric Davis and I'll just
read something I pulled from Wikipedia
real brief if you have no idea who Eric
Davis is he's American writer scholar
journalists and public speaker whose
writings have ranged from rock criticism
the culture analysis to creative
explorations of esoteric mysticism he's
offer author of a few books one of them
tech gnosis and most recently high
weirdness and he has this excellent
podcast expanding Minds if you haven't
expanding mine if you haven't listened
to it I'd highly recommend it I was
actually on it
maybe I got year or so ago we talked
about culture war many tribes and
stoicism so what's gonna happen today
Eric is going to present his thoughts on
the high weirdness of our situation that
we're in and then I'll warm up with a
few questions and then we'll have
questions for the group if you have any
questions write in the chat box it's
gonna be on YouTube so if you don't want
to be on YouTube just ask me too
read it on your behalf and I will do so
and and total we have 60 minutes
together that being said I will hand it
over to you Eric
great thanks so much thanks Peter for
inviting me and nice to see everybody
showing up I recognize a few friendly
familiar faces
so Peter mentioned I just published a
book recently called high weirdness
drugs esoterica and visionary experience
in the 1970s and when I started this
project I was really just interested in
you know some psychedelic and visionary
figures from the 70s philip k dick
terence mckenna and Robert Anton Wilson
and I just sort of noticed some
similarities between what they were
doing and so I really wanted to tell a
story about the 1970s and about these
wild and woolly Psychonauts and writers
who were both visionary in their
experiences visionary and extreme and
their experiences and in their writings
but as I was running more and more and
kind of like the world was changing
around me I started to realize more and
more that I was using these things to
kind of try to understand something
about what's happening to us today and
while I didn't end up spending that much
time in the book reflecting on how this
weirdness reflected the conditions today
I did I did some as I spent like a year
doing podcasts about the book which are
you know kind of trailed off now
although I I did an audiobook version
that came out earlier this year and so I
did some more press around that and some
more discussions and I really like the
way the audio book came out a lot of
people find it a little easier to take
than the somewhat academic density of
the of the book but as I was doing these
talks I realized more and more I was
just talking about what was going on now
the politics of consciousness now the
politics of psychedelics now how why are
all these things going on now what do we
how do we navigate a meltdown and
consensus reality which has a kind of
psychedelic quality not necessarily a
particularly pleasant one
you know and that's part of what I was
writing about as well it's not some kind
of happy fluff
the psychedelic sort of ideology that
you're getting these days but really
more wrestling with some of the darker
sides of it the relationship to
psychopathology the relationship to
paranoia what happens when you have a
break what happens when you have an
extraordinary experience you can't
integrate and what happens especially
when those things start to resonate and
reflect on actual political realities
that themselves aren't particularly rosy
I think one thing that I would want to
say just to connect it like why is he
talking about the 70s is that in a lot
of ways if we if we can look back at all
and find a moment in American history
and I think this is you know as true I
have to say North American history
perhaps but certainly in the United
States that the closest era that we have
to what works I think a lot of people
are experiencing now is the early 70s
because it was a time of of
disappointment of frustration there was
a lot of divergence in identity in fact
a lot of the sort of multicultural world
that we're we're familiar with now was
in many ways kind of both celebrated and
engineered at that time in history so
there's more and more lifestyles and
more and more perspectives there's more
and more multiculturalism going on in
good and in challenging ways and at the
same time there was an overall vibe of
bummer you know there was a energy
crisis in the early 70s there was the
rise of the modern terrorist you know
then it was a lot of high hijackings of
planes but there were lots of bombs
going off in the United States in Europe
there was a sense of tremendous tension
there was still a lot of racial tension
there was this endless war going on in
Vietnam and there was increasing
evidence that there was like radical
malfeasance at the heart of the US
government in the presidency and a sense
of a tremendous social divide and and
and also since the things weren't really
necessarily gonna get better that the
revolution that everybody thought was
gonna happen sometime in the 60s whether
it was political or or
metaphysical or psychedelic or all of it
together that it just wasn't gonna
happen and so people were kind of thrown
back on their own devices and had to
make make their own meaning they had to
produce you know participate in a kind
of sense making and from our distance
now we can see a lot of the ways that
that went south you know a lot of the
what we've come to call the New Age and
a lot of psychotherapy groups and a lot
of cults a lot of new religious
movements a lot of you know gurus from
the east like that was the time when all
this stuff really got rolling kind of in
the wake of the disappointments of the
counterculture but the sense that
something else had to happen we had that
we had to make meaning together
individually and so the whole mode of
the seeker as someone who was you know
perhaps looking for more spiritual
solutions but in many cases and this was
certainly very true for the people that
I was writing about is that they all had
political motivations in a weird way for
plunging into psychedelic experience in
their own strange experiments they
weren't like dropping out exactly it was
more a sense that since reality is sort
of incomprehensible or spiraling out of
control why not see if like this kind of
stuff is going to work and I think the
final little motif that comes up that's
definitely related to some of the
mimetic Tribe stuff not just the the
sense of multiple perspectives in
society being forcibly expand to
acknowledge these multiple perspectives
but also some of the inherent you know
rabbit holing that goes on and
particularly the rise of conspiracy
theory and this is the final kind of
connection that I'd make is that
paranoia was like a dominant emotion in
these beers particularly in the early
seventies there's there was always
paranoia in the counterculture because
there was so much infiltration by the
FBI by police COINTELPRO in fact a lot
of years people thought you know all you
guys are just being paranoid and then
like when we actually find out how much
malfeasance was being practiced by these
hidden agencies who were not just
observing but acting as agent
provocateurs and
you know making political moves now as
well as bumping people off I mean it was
really a you know nasty scene but a lot
of paranoia was justified but it became
into a sort of more you know psychic
cosmological frame in the 1970s and if
you go through or especially early 70s
popular culture which is saturated with
sort of psychedelia and melancholy and a
kind of technological frustration and
paranoia you see a lot of the great kind
of conspiracy movies come up in the in
the early to mid 1970s that that's
another kind of point of resonance and
finally along these lines just to kind
of underscore a connection and then we
can talk more about now the chapters
that I wrote about Robert Anton Wilson
are particularly important in the zone
because Robert Anton Wilson wrote a book
with a co-author Robert Shaye they wrote
it in the late 60s mostly but it came
out in 1975 called
illuminatus and in Illuminatus they play
in a an archaic romping goofy kind of
brilliant kind of satirical kind of Pulp
Fiction e-way with the ideas of
conspiracy basically idea that all
conspiracies are true and in that a game
they have this all this lower about the
Illuminati which is partly based on
actual conspiracy theory partly based on
actual history and then partly stuff
that they were just inventing and making
up drawing from a cult fiction and
science fiction and weird stuff and you
know making a lot of it up but in many
ways the environment the vibe of the
book is very resonant now particularly
when we think about how central
conspiracy theory has come to be in
terms of consensus reality how to think
about it how it works and in in some
ways how to sort of move through it like
rather than just put it aside and say oh
that's all the crazy stuff that the
people who can't think are indulging
themselves in instead going but you know
actually we have to look at it because
there's some stuff in there that is
factually true and there's some stuff in
there even more so that it is
allegorically true meaning that it's
like okay it might not be literally true
but
it's a really good myth or fiction or
allegory for other sorts of social
processes and transformations that the
mainstream can't recognize because it
runs on denying them so as a thinking
person as a meta thinker as a sense
maker you have to kind of go through
aspects of the conspiracy world but how
do you do it not lose your lose the plot
and in some ways I try to read
Illuminatus and Wilson's own thought and
in some sense he was he was kind of he
was stoic in some ways but he certainly
was a philosophically informed weirdo
thinker that he kind of in a way model
ways of passing through in a way the
chapel perilous of that the conspiracy
and esoteric experience and you know
radical D realization of consensus
reality leads you to and in some ways I
feel like that's part of the job of the
edge thinker now is to be willing to
step aside or step off the whatever
remains of a kind of consensus
mainstream view but do so in a very
pragmatic tactical and well practiced
way in order to to extend the the space
of collective sense making and not
become overly lured into positions that
I think ultimately undermine that
collective embodied empirical
relationship or practice that is called
upon us when reality as a consensus
thing and even as a physical space-time
matrix is is clearly you know crumbling
and transforming so I think I'll stop
there for the intro yeah that's that's
good Robert Anton Wilson was a huge
influence on me and his sort of
guerrilla ontology you know how you
purposely expose yourself to these
bizarre ideas to kind of create that
cognitive distance so you can kind of be
comfortable with them in a way
and I find that very helpful especially
with the conspiracy theory narratives
because if you just dive into that like
a performative agnostic and act as if
it's true it's like radical paranoia
overcomes you and then if you don't have
a good relationship with that you're
gonna run into some of these narratives
so there's I'm at the stall here people
are know I'm using this like term
liminal war instead of the culture world
this is a liminal state right now and
there's like a war in order to kind of
Gaslight our minds and to believe a
certain narratives and what is your
sense of the state especially with the
conspiracy theory stuff coming on like
you and on and all this energy that's
happened in the noosphere right now yeah
well one of the ways that I deal with it
is I try to try to act like a like an
anthropologist or a cultural historian
or something like that which is that I
don't try to put on my mind the decision
about what it means or what truth is in
it or because in some ways if you go
look if you go into the zone if you go
down the rabbit hole looking to figure
out what you think is true you're
already hooked in a certain way like
they've already that's the bait or
that's some of the bait and it doesn't
mean that that's not something you're
gonna want to know and want to do but I
try to like get at it from a kind
another angle and I think one of the
ways to do it is also sort of be looking
for the al the allegorical meaning of it
so that you're not either going yes or
no so it's not like oh I find out okay
you say whatever Bill Gates is this and
that and okay there's the vaccine is he
still implanted chips in it dadada and
that's actually happening you know I
have enough investment in let's call it
what what remains of journalistic
integrity and scientific procedures and
conventional forms of authority that I
don't believe that but if I go in there
and I go okay no that's bullsh you're
just crazy then all I can really do if I
don't even want to empathize with you is
maybe say well you're just you're
paranoid and you didn't you were you
didn't have her
education so you're not really talking
bah-bah-bah basically just be kind of a
snob to write them off that's not that's
not what I'm talking about that's not
this perilous path so it's to go in
there and actually really reckon with
the allegory what is the historical
condition that is being narrative eyes
door mythologized
with elements of truth I'm not saying
it's all bullshit I'm just saying that
it gets constellated as a myth because
the myth has something to say that in
many ways is more well certainly more
convincing to me but often more
pertinent than the specifics of a
particular scenario which is you know
right lies right next to all sorts of
other scenarios so it's almost like
you're going in there trying to get a
picture of a bigger well it's almost
like a dream analysis where you go into
the dream you don't the surface of the
dream the details of the surface of the
dream maybe they're useful maybe they're
not but the pattern of the dream and
most importantly the effect of the dream
is significant and that's another part
of I think being a sense maker today and
you talk about being embodied and the
embodiment to me isn't just that you're
grounded in your own physical practice
your own capacity to be you know strong
and balanced and healthy as you can be
within this just as a way to keep some
ground in the picture but the body is
also the emotions it's also a fact and
add it's important to actually stress
that little technical difference because
when we say emotions we we tend to mean
the emotions that we can name that are
I'm feeling fear right now I'm really
scared or like oh you're you're being
you know oh this is joyful I'm really so
happy that you said that and those are
we can identify emotion happiness
emotion fear effect is something a
little bit below that that clear surface
we may be motivated by ethics that we're
not aware of um it's not quite like
instinct that's a little strong it's a
little behavioral affect is more like a
feeling but a feeling that isn't
necessarily acknowledged now here's a
really clear example that plays into
both the conversation about mimetic
tribes and conspiracy theory but but
from the past so it's easier to see
which is like if you look at the rise of
right-wing radio you know let's say in
the 80's 90's you know right around that
but whenever you tapped into it so goes
on all you all you want and you know it
as part of this Robert Anton Wilson
practice of listening to people that you
don't agree with it really sort of like
wrestling with it and trying not to just
write it off but not trying to believe
it but kind of resonating with it is it
metaphor I use a lot like what does it
mean to resonate with a you know a white
nationalist and just what does that mean
like how are they go where are they
coming from where are they coming from
and to me that's part of just as a
little side note that's part of again
being a kind of practitioner of this
liminal space is to develop the capacity
for real resonance which doesn't mean
agreement but it it definitely it
doesn't it also doesn't mean putting a
label on someone so you can just put it
over there on the other side of the
table
it means like what does this feel like
what are the cluster of images and
emotions and stories and histories that
are coming together in this position of
a contemporary white nationalist or a
Boogaloo boy or whatever the heck it is
and try and allowing yourself to
resonate as a form of understanding that
doesn't imply any kind of agreement or
support of these positions so that's
just how I do I mean I'm saying everyone
should do it but that's what I mean by
being kind of an anthropologist as a way
of moving through these worlds so to
take the example so I used to listen to
a lot of right-wing radio when I was
driving alone I just go to the am dial
and and I was you know I listened to it
and whatever and here you know it's a
great example when I'm talking but you
can listen to the arguments they say
this they spin this news story this way
people call up and they're they don't
have a lot of good knowledge and they're
come you know they're referring to
things that never happened or whatever
the you can stay on that level of like
language and argument and information
and history and whatever okay fine
but after a while I was like wait that
stuff is all just like a play it's all
just it's like a again a lure
what's really
going on here is just the generation of
a few basic effects so you develop the
sense of being out of control and then
you develop a sense of being righteous
you develop a sense of resentment who a
lot a resentment so that the story you
could almost look at like what's being
managed here are these very powerful
effects that are collectively organized
and then latched on to various talking
points so once you get into the way in
which right-wing radio like you know and
all the political parties do this I'm
not that the left does it just as much
where there's certain effects that are
generated and then they're attached to
particular talking points or narrative
events that are going on in the news
cycle as a way to give them more weight
on the liberal side let's say the when
they were jailing the the children of
undocumented you know people crossing
the border and it was you know
understandable response and yet the way
in which the child and the cage and all
that was was sort of manipulated if you
will through the news cycle among
liberal progressives and you could even
see the way people were like that's my
line in the sand that's it I can't take
it anymore
was like oh that's more of that stuff so
that effect awareness beginning getting
wise and that's part of resonance part
of resonating with somebody else is to
get their effect which you can
appreciate even if you don't if you
don't believe it's justifiable you know
you don't we actually deserve that kind
of resentment man you're doing pretty
good or you really don't agree with the
way that it's attached itself to a kind
of narrative but the effect itself is
more like in your body it's more like
that's actually there whether you want
it to be or you haven't a story about it
or not so that's kind of a way that that
I try to move through this stuff and
it's hard it's really hard with
conspiracy theory I don't particularly
like it very much anymore I used to be
interested in it more when I was younger
and I was into Robert Anton Wilson and
it was kind of a thrill because it was a
way of playing
with my own paranoia as a kind of you
know like sniffing glue or something
like whoa I'm getting really paranoid
had a weird dream and like Wow
and now it's I feel I tend to feel more
burdened by the terror of confusion that
exists behind people's convictions it's
like I can't believe the conviction I'm
sorry I just you don't have the evidence
to produce this coherent a model of this
entire other nefarious multi-tentacled
historical event that the rest of us
don't really see that way I just don't
buy your conviction
so what effectively are you doing with
your conviction what is behind that and
then there's the sense of tremendous out
of being out of control of not knowing
how do we proceed when we don't know
when we really don't know you know and
that's part of what this trickier work
of sense making is is to become more
sensible about how we proceed when we
really can't know about a lot of things
or when we know that we're being you
know liminal II hit or manipulated or
drawn into things so how do we move
through that how do we keep talking how
do we keep building coherent models of
the world and you know there's a lot
that's it's not easy work and I think
there's a lot of easier ways to handle
it and so you get around peoples effect
and it's a you know so it's sort of
tough so I try to I I do not close the
door on conspiracy stuff I stay up on it
I have particular opinions opinions
about Q and on and and could you know
talk more about that but I also try to
limit my I don't want to become like the
conspiracy guy because it's just too
unhealthy for me after a while like I
can feel that this is not this isn't
good for you you know growing up yeah
yeah
I'll pivot to the questions and I was a
lot of good questions in the chat box I
think we were talking when I came on
your podcast last about like method
acting different reality tunnels in
order to achieve that and maybe this is
something we can talk about offline
at a later date but we have a wisdom gym
here as a mission of the stoah and the
whole idea here is develop like a good
relationship with unknowingness and then
how to do that what kind of life
practices can we do that in an ecology
that would help with that and so we can
have that communicative prowess when we
can method act someone into reality
tunnel but are with ourselves to that we
can like stay in the state of
unknowingness without getting seduced
your gaslighted or whatever so I think
this is a good question to start off
with from Joshua Joshua would you like
to unmute yourself and ask your question
to Eric my question is how would you say
that code is weird I'm asking because
that's really great and I didn't really
define what is the term weird so this
lets me do do it I really appreciate
that question in in in high weirdness I
use the category of the weird to talk
about a couple of things one is the
sense of liminality that happens when
consensus your consensus reality or
ordinary reality begins to melt down
but particularly I was interested in
those experiences and feelings and
relationships that happen when you're
not invoking some kind of otherworldly
mystical or religious power so I like
take an example and then I'll bring it
into the co vid you know like let's say
you have what it feels like a prophetic
dream
you know you like you had the dream you
wrote it down two days later the thing
you wrote down exactly happened to
yellow Chevrolet pulled up and almost
hit the baby or whatever the thing is
it's in my book so if you are someone
who who you know accepts multiple
dimensions fate it's all written
beforehand need a large abstractions
about the true metaphysical reality of
the world you might say that oh my god
has proves that there's that you can
your mind can see into the future this
proves that the future is already
written or some large abstraction that
you're using this to come
but then there's another approach which
is the kind of approach that I'm trying
to talk about it and just you know
really actually celebrate in some ways
which is you just go yeah it was weird
and you're like what do you mean by that
we use the term all the time something's
weird
oh it's weird as a weird dream weird
person weird what are we actually saying
we don't really pay attention to the
word we don't think of it as an actual
category the way that real is a category
or the losery is a category or uncanny
even as a category it's kind of like the
uncanny but it's a little bit darker a
little bit more materialistic in a in a
material way not a not a gravity way and
so I'm really just interested in tracing
this among people who are having these
experiences that have so many religious
and mystical and cosmological elements
in them that their ability some of the
time not all the time but their ability
some of the time to stay grounded in
that leads to what I call weird
naturalism and what I mean by that and
nuts will get us to Cove it is that just
this world without invoking any
metaphysical principles mystical things
God's other dimensions just this world
with you know some physics thrown in is
or can be weird and whether that's
because anomalies keep happening no
matter where we however we try to solve
them maybe this would thing looked like
an anomaly and then later on we learned
actually wasn't you can totally be
explained oh look there's another
anomaly on the horizon oh we never we
never transcend this character and then
you get involved into actual anomalies
that you know depending on where you sit
and what you look at things that are
characterized by the paranormal or
things that are characterized by high
dose psychedelic experience we're just
weird shit happens hard to say what's
going on here and rather than say oh
that means there's another world or that
means there's the truth behind this one
I just want to say no know where we are
this place where we already are is weird
and if you go looking for it you're
really gonna find it and sometimes it
comes looking for you
and that sense of breaking down or that
sense of reality shifting that can be
produced through all sorts of things
including conspiracy theory including
you know learning and reading including
having these experiences are all ways of
encountering the weird so today I think
though that I mean kovat is weird in a
lot of ways because it was unexpected it
is invisible but not the physiological
effects of it are very peculiar the as
far as I can tell you know I don't I
don't spend all my time trying to keep
up on on the science but I actually know
some people who do and I talked to them
about what they're what they're doing
it's it's extraordinary what we don't
really know is is it affect the nervous
system maybe it's maybe it's affecting
the nervous system principally and
actually the lung stuff is only a second
that you know and then the rates of
reactions and how varied they are and
the quality of the turnover and whatever
so it's just created this I mean it's
really pulled the rug out from under us
and then you get into all the social
things the fact that we have to then
navigate a social reality where various
authorities are both you know creating
demanding specific situations about gas
you know masks and closing stores and
all this like actual shift in our social
reality but beyond that is the sense
that we're almost inevitably in a
conspiratorial situation we're like we
have no choice but to wrestle with the
distinct possibility that some of this
stuff has multiple purposes and I'm not
that interested in that the whole thing
is engineered or this and that above a
blah I find it more likely that maybe
something slipped out of a lab in China
they don't want to really tell you about
it but in a way that doesn't matter
you know because the the the conspiracy
the link to the origins is usually less
important to what people are how people
are actually weaponizing and exploiting
the situation as it evolves and of
course we can see that so in order to
really try to understand where we are we
have no choice but to kind of go into
a realm of the unknown where inevitably
certain kinds of patterns that are more
archetypal or mythical take the stage
where you start wondering about well
maybe this is a kind of who would be
behind it oh it's the you know the dark
room with all the people in there hands
on the levers manipulating things you
like no no it can't be that far it can't
be that for but yet there's something
kind of curious about X&Y or the look
how quickly we're thinking about oh I
can't wait for contract tracing so I can
go out and enjoy my life and you're like
well what a year ago I was already
horrified with the loss of privacy that
we had that and now I'm like looking for
with it what happened to me so if you're
paying attention you enter into what
Wilson called a kind of Chapel perilous
when you no longer have a really
concrete way of organizing the totality
of your experience and this sort of
strongly supported sense that there are
multiple ways of looking at the thing
that nobody really knows what's going on
the no one's really driving the bus and
that the bus is kind of creating down
the hill and so the weirdness is to not
deny the peculiarity of the situation by
holding on to some oh it's going to go
back to the way it was or oh it's I can
just trust all these agencies or what I
get from these news feeds is what's
really going on it so I can feel okay
and you know stay calm
sorry I don't think you can do that but
what do you do then then you kind of
accept that you're in this situation of
the weird and then use practical tools
and your own self work as a way of
staying awake and sane and grounded in
relationship to it but I think the
weirdness is it's almost like a perfect
example of it because it's not
metaphysical but yet people think about
it that way you know whether they are
think like oh it's a message from the
from the earth you know this is the vet
you know that the virus is the vaccine
it's the thing that's waking us up or no
it's this instrument of malfeasant
you know New World Order you know
transhumanist Illuminati okay so now
then we're in another myth but even if
you try to stay really close to the
facts on the ground and a really secular
and grounded way and whatever you're
also just seeing the like the
instability of scientific knowledge the
incapacity of all of these authorities
to really handle things in the way that
you would imagine that their authority
in there and their training and their
their public role would would illuminate
so the sense of being unmoored of being
a sea of scrambling like all of those
are actual experiences but they're not
just you like oh it's my emotions I
can't handle it or I'm scared or
whatever no no the thing itself is going
Wiggy like the actual historical moment
is getting weird and that shifts to my
mind shifts the way you experience it
because it's not like your fault you're
not expected to know the answer you know
and that's where we get into this not
knowing thing and that one of the
problems right now is that everybody's
so used to knowing that even people who
have no business coming to some kind of
unusual conviction about what's going on
based on their the information they're
taking in or their quality of critical
thought or anything like that
they're so convinced because that's what
everybody does is what they do on the TV
these you know this these got a
point-counterpoint they each yell at
each other each trying to get each other
on their own terms into their own axioms
so being able to move through the fog of
war or through the fog of information
war without pretending it's not going on
but also not being overwhelmed by that
is a very particular art that I think
resonates very much with the sense
making practices this not knowing
practices and it's where in a way people
who are drawn to this kind of thinking
you know it's like this is the metal
meets the road kind of thing and this is
we're actually having to do it
and stumble through it but to my mind
it's like it's ever more clear that it's
you know that there's another way
through this kind of stuff that's really
important for at least some of us to
keep alive because the if only because
the way the conviction you know
poisons our vision of the capacity of
being able to steer through this either
individually or collectively because
it's so concrete eyes that it doesn't
allow any shift so you get all these
polarizations and then restaging of the
the fight and so now there's a fight
about masks and you have it on your this
and that it uh and you're like wow i i'd
rather say this is weird in a way it's
almost comforting i hope that makes
sense we have a question that kind of
can take onto that nicely Travis man you
had a question Eric so what is your
assessment of Robert Anton Wilson legacy
in terms of kind of espousing this
generalized agnosticism you spoke about
some of the failed collective
sense-making experiences from the 70s do
you have any examples of like successes
in Robert Anton Wilson legacy not just
on an individual level of coming in to
terms with the weirdness that we face on
a daily basis but also like societally
this generalized agnosticism being
applied to forming groups and things of
that nature those are great questions
I'll do my best I wish I could have more
on the last one that I then I think I do
I think that you know the legacy of
Wilson is a very interesting one because
again as I was writing this I was like
going more and more like whoa this is
just this is so similar to what's
happening at the time I was writing in
particular was the lead that I was
finishing around the lead up to 2 2016 2
the Trump election and there was all the
you know paper the Frog
stuff and all the sense that a certain
kind of internet savvy prankster
nihilist humor mode was being used
weapon had been weaponized and was being
used very forcibly in order to you know
do information warfare at least online
how influential that was in the end it's
very very hard to say but it clearly was
got a lot of press and got people aware
of it and I think it was influential in
in some ways and and continues to be in
in different ways I think it's it never
stays put it kind of changes and then
then it breaks down and other things can
absorb it and you know but it was very
appointed and without going into
specifics there's things about Wilson in
the in the late sixties and early
seventies where they were doing exactly
that they were doing pranks that took
advantage of other people's conspiracy
paranoia's in order to just fuck with
them and to do it in a way not in a mean
way in sort of a spirit of anarchic you
know yippie sort of like countercultural
politics to make fun of them and to also
create room and I think that's that's
you know in a way that's the example of
what you're talking about but it's also
is an example of something I won't say
failed but maybe by its very nature is
difficult to organize so if you look at
both the appease and at them at the more
small-scale discord Ian's who were more
anarchic
in the 60s in the 70s you know they were
using a kind of Zen prankster
playfulness in order to reflect back the
unacknowledged contradictions or
investments of the mainstream society
you know like like going to going to
levitate the Pentagon in 1967 like
that's absurd Pentagon is not gonna go
up into the space nor is it going to
turn orange and yet by celebrating the
idea that we were all going to come
together all these different tribes and
you know weirdos from the lower Eastside
and you know civil rights people
and and communists and whatever we're
gonna come together and live you know
levitate the Pentagon Pentagon it
created a kind of social methods that
actually said something about the
movement and its capacity to reimagine
the future not just to respond and react
to the concrete power dynamics of the
present but to imagine something greater
than that and to do so with humor and
with a kind of not taking herself
seriously that was also very serious so
that's a subtle set of feelings and and
and and expressions that in the late 60s
definitely had a role I mean part of
political protest in this late 60s had
this like prankster open-ended kind of
quality to it but it doesn't really lead
itself lend itself very well to let's
say conventional party politics and
that's part of the point and so one of
the ways you can demonstrate that with
with particularly Robert Anton Wilson
stuff and the kind of pranks they did is
you're like you don't really have a good
example of that kind of pranking
attitude you have some with the Church
of the SubGenius they kind of carried it
forward it was a little bit less
political in some ways or that the
targets were easier making fun of
Christianity you know making but you
know but it it still had that anarchic
open-ended humorous but but you know
politically informed quality to it but
it's not really till you get to the flip
side of you know the meme magic
all right guys in in 2015-2016
that you actually see something that's
that political except now it's from the
other side you know they were anarchists
so there was always some libertarian you
know anti state attitudes inside Robert
Anton Wilson stuff so it's not they're
not just figures of the left but still
there would they would have nothing to
do with this kind of monster or in a way
sorry should I'm falling into a myth but
uh that kind of that kind of activity
and yet there you are looking at its
logic so as somebody who's like a Robert
Anton Wilson fan and thinks he's
important thinks he's even politically
important I got a deal with that and and
it's not easy
because I know again it's that I I mean
I hate to say this because it's not a
conclusion that I want to either believe
or even have to reckon with but I do
think that some of this stuff we're
talking about it just doesn't work on a
large scale and so you will you get back
into that thing of they're sort of not
secret schools but just sort of under
the radar nodes of ways of looking at
reality that they have a certain kind of
tentativeness and an acceptance of
ambiguity and acceptance of multiplicity
that isn't like powerlessness it's not
like postmodern relativism or like oh
everybody's story is equal nobody knows
someone I talk about at all but it does
acknowledge a kind of a power of those
multiple viewpoints that most political
parties most people shrink away from
they don't want to deal with that and so
I when I when you ask about what are
these forms that it could take that
aren't just individual that are beyond
what like this is which is a you know a
kind of tentative node off to the side
where the individuals involved are
plugged into some pretty interesting
things but they tend to also be further
networks of this kind of interest ease
place rather than something that
coalesce is and coheres in a very
obvious way such that it could become
another obvious mimetic tribe and that's
both its strength and its weakness it's
like you can wake up in the midst of any
historical situation but the terms that
you're waking up in may not be
translatable to the majority of people
who are going on in that situation so if
you're interested in how waking up
applies and is live through a moment of
historical transition or transformation
or breakdown or whatever it's tough you
know I want to say that that in a way
it's like you know what was the what was
that phrase let me just look over here
oh yeah the whole idea of the invisible
college so the idea of the invisible
college which is sort of a motif and
some you know conspiracy theories to was
a way that the Royal Society first
started to refer to itself in the 17th
century in the early 17th century when
the Rosicrucians were happening and like
science hadn't quite crystallized as
like an alternate form of belief and it
was still embedded in kind of esoteric
ideas but people were sensing that we
were moving out of the Middle Ages that
there were new forms of government that
were coming something about reason was
letting things happen it was a
transition point a liminal point and the
idea of an invisible College is that
there's you're sort of like you have
colleagues everywhere it's not very
visible you are engaged in an active
political life but it's not doesn't
Massa fight doesn't it sounds obvious in
a way and it sets the stage for
something else
and you know I think that's also a
really good thing to remember when
you're feeling lost or when you're
feeling like what how does this actually
help you know is that you you can't know
how these very tentative relationships
or the practices that you have now are
ceding or setting the stage for
something else that's going to happen
which it might be very different you
know we might be changing the way we
think in some fundamental ways 50 years
down the line or whatever I mean I don't
want to get into all the different
things that could be happening in the
future but because it's so oppressive
and overwhelming but I think it's it's
it's it's very good to honor the tiny
little bit that you're doing it's like
you know in a way it's almost like being
in a you know if there's like a wisdom
teacher around you and this is someone
who's like they're on it they got the
goods like they're you know whatever we
think about it religiously or
philosophically but someone who's really
like a wise person and he or she is
creating a scene where people go but you
know if you go to these things you look
around like a lot of people therefore
kind of weird reasons and some of them
aren't so smart and some of them are are
kind of gossipy and so you don't agree
with and then you're not even sure why
you're there like why am I really being
here
and you can you can say oh this is all
just kind of pointless but that's that's
like the way like wisdom you know isn't
doesn't manifest on the front page so it
has a
quality of kind of through the cracks
and it may not help but it kind of also
has to be what it is and so I feel like
this kind of thing that you're pointing
to it almost inevitably has that quality
to it and that the best thing we can do
is to keep being is robustly collective
and connected as we can be to not sort
of just give up and become a monad to
stay in body but also stay in body
together even if it's just 30 people on
a zoom call or whatever that this is it
in a way for this right now
and to be okay with that degree of des
centeredness even though it's so
obviously not sufficient to you know
fight back systemic racism or meted you
know narratives being crammed on a
throat from the CDC or from Bill Gates
or from The Kooks on on cue and on or
whatever it is it's like it's this is a
drop in the bucket but it's also where
we are and and so I hope I hope that's a
sum provide something so we have about
10 minute or eight minutes I think we
can sneak in another question Eric yes
is okay if we go over a little bit or do
we get this answer this question then
wrap it up great okay Lisa Norton you
had a question about Mark Fisher which I
was kind of interested in trying to meet
yourself and asking yeah Eric thank you
apologies I haven't read your new book
but I was wondering if you connected
your how you Square or orient your
notion of weirdness to people like Mark
Fischer's the weird and the eerie or
some of the people like Levy Bryant or
Timothy Martin great thanks for that
question that's a nice that's that's
it's a good one because I got Fisher
stuff relatively late into the writing
but I did manage to find some very
wonderful overlaps that were really
really really important to me
the the main one that really helped me
is the difference which I talked about
in the introduction between the uncanny
and the weird and the uncanny is sort of
more
more like acceptable notions certainly
in academia it's kind of like already
has it sort of Zone in a way that the
weird doesn't I think there's actually
some really concrete issues of you know
demographics and and cultural class
behind that the weird is a lowbrow form
the uncanny is a higher brow form but
more importantly is that that is that
the uncanny is essentially psychological
so the way that Fisher talks about it is
he says the uncanny all ultimately
refers in its the internal family drama
that's left its trace that then is
discovered again in exteriority whereas
the weird is the relationship to the
outside and that difference for me is
totally key I mean it's really important
is that the weird is not just my feeling
the weird is of a tenor an ambiance of a
relation to an outside or an other that
is ultimately unassimilable and that's
where it gets into the triple o stuff
which is also very much a part of it I I
got to hang out with Morton a buncha at
Rice and I read it a lot of those guys
and I loved it it was like the biggest
kind of philosophical discovery that I
had had in many many years where I felt
oh yeah this is this stuff is really
really good for what I'm doing even if
I'm doing it you directing it is
somewhat different direct different
directions and there again what I really
appreciate when they talk my whole idea
about weird naturalism is not that
different than weird essentialism that
that Morton talks about and not spacing
it's named the guy who teaches in North
Africa why am I forgetting is name
anyway and the idea there is just that
we are in a we are really in a world of
objects there are real things everywhere
it's not just an illusion in your mind
it's not just some you know my
expression of Maya and those kind of old
mystical psychedelic ideas which I don't
think are very helpful anymore we're
actually embedded in all sorts of you
know real networks with relationality
with all of these objects on many many
four levels of scale but that there's an
essential opacity to those objects so
we're in this weird situation where
we're in relationship with something we
can never capture with our
representations that can never be
perfectly translated but it's not just
an isolated reflectivity we're all I
have is my own projections that's what
the difference is is that there is
something like an encounter it's just
that the encounter can't be adequately
represented and it can't be captured and
it can't be entirely directed and the
way that's part of its strength
that's certainly part of its political
strength and say it's ecological
strength is we have to really open up to
the fact that we are embedded in objects
and hyper objects that are so far beyond
our capacity even collectively to
understand and yet we have to act from
that responsibility and that awareness
and the way that I take that in my kind
of more visionary and psychedelic way in
the book is to talk about what's
happening in extraordinary experience is
something like this encounter where even
the projections don't really aren't
really adequate anymore and yet it
remains unassimilable so it doesn't give
you a revelation so the minute you go
and all I talk to the mine you know like
psychedelic people oh I talk to hit the
mind of the of the planet and it told me
that the covet is part of a healing
process like no you've already lost it
I'm not saying you didn't encounter the
mind of Gaia it's just that that
encounter scrambles as much as it
initiates and that that's our weird
situation and we have to move within
that both the limitations and I think
the openness of that situation so again
and again it's like relationships to
exteriority to material conditions to
historical material conditions but also
to recognizing the fundamental weirdness
in that relation that also offers room
to maneuver that a strict determinism or
a strict physicalism doesn't at all and
you know I guess we could talk more
about
triple o and how different flavors go in
different directions around science
around determinism around you know human
psychic activity and it does it have any
purpose and and things like that but uh
but yeah I really appreciate you
pointing that stuff out because it was
it was really important to me in
developing the kind of argumentation and
our armature of the book great thank you
so we have a lot of awesome questions
unfortunately can't get to them all
today so err who would love to have you
come back another time
I need any closing thoughts you have for
us at the store no this is great I mean
I really you know I really admire your
work in particular and I thought I'm
still kind of you know wrestling with
some of the issues that you brought up
that we were talking about on on
expanding mind and and III think we have
no chime een it's funny it's like I
guess this is the thing I'll leave you
leave you with is that as someone who's
been very interested in spiritual
practices and psychedelics in these sort
of internal seeking narratives even as
I'm also interested in politics and
history and science and physical you
know Natural History and the you know
the route the real place we are real
that you know there's always the sense
that there's something indulgent or
narcissistic or deluded about spiritual
work or philosophical spirit what
everyone call that it's that it's you
know it's only because of your privilege
and you're doing it to like just deal
with your neuroses and get over with it
and get get out there and start doing
stuff and I you know and sort of a not
you know not necessarily a happy news
way but that the value of that work in
my life and in the people around me who
seem awake now that I can have a
conversation with it's a real
conversation almost invariably means
there's something like that going on in
their life too so to me it's very clear
the the concrete payoff value of this
kind of work at a time like this and not
saying that it came
you know it can lead you foul to of one
little side note just because we talked
about cue and on it's one of the reasons
that I had been very I've been paying a
lot of tension to it recently what there
was that there was a noticeable uptick
noticed by me and many other people who
I know personally and observers and
other people I didn't know who reflected
on it a noticeable uptick in the last
couple of months among alternative
medicine yoga psychedelic Burning Man
those that kind of those kind of zones
of straight-up cueing on myth many often
times they didn't even know what it was
and I was like whoa something has
happened so obviously a lot of this kind
of spiritual stuff can can you know go
awry and in a variety of ways and in a
way the history of the seventies is all
you need to know to show that but that
this particular quality of adding a
philosophical self-reflection and a
certain kind of logic of sort of self
work I don't want to say self-control
but some of that kind of willingness to
limit and constrain certain aspects of
the self in light of other demands and
in playing with that some of that
discipline as part of a way of going
deeper into the mystery rather than that
it just arranging an individual self
that these practices are really helpful
right now they're really good and that
we need them and that through them we
can also form kinds of collectivities
and relationships and conversations that
just have a coherence and an honesty and
you know a kind of what is it as sort of
like you know in a way the the the
quality of the the warrior quality of
being a you know awake and staring your
fear in its face it's like we have like
fear confusion but there's that same
like just get up stand up again okay
there hope you felt get up it got up
again that kind of practice or that kind
of discipline seems really key right now
and so you know I really appreciate the
way that you and your communities are
weaving these things together as well
yeah yeah and my sense is as stoicism
could have a role in helping with this
so in a moment if you can stay around
for just one more minute you can listen
to some of the upcoming things in our
wisdom Jim but thanks so much for coming
on my friend it was greatly appreciated
we would love to have you back to tease
out all these different threats oh yeah
so yeah let's talk about a couple of
events in the wisdom Jim we have a fewer
facilitators here Travis man you have
something called breaking the frame if
you can go of Newton tell us what that
is yeah certainly so breaking the frame
is actually directly related to a lot of
the stuff that we talked about here so I
some relational exercises through which
we try to cultivate intellectual
humility and cognitive flexibility by
examining our own relationship with our
worldviews so you can sign up I am
posting a link in the chat right now for
the registration there hope to see you
there thank you and I really like that's
like kind of adopting a narrative and
then breaking and finding the
alternative one and jumping from
narrative narrative
Tyson you have a flowing through a
knowingness knowingness that is for me a
session that has come out of me wanting
to deepen my relationship with weirdness
and unknowingness and so we practice
freestyle rap and spoken word as a group
to really come into a deeper
relationship with like the unknowingness
of creativity and can see how well we
can trust ourselves to open up and say
that first word and then to see we can
enter that space of flow together and
it's a really wonderful way to get to
know people in a in a session that just
really embraces the weirdness and yeah I
look forward to seeing some of you there
yeah that one that session particularly
pushing me at the edge of my comfort
zone so I hope to see Eric there next is
that next Saturday and then as Stephen
Beattie you have a the stoic breath on
Sundays yes that's right Sunday at 10:00
the stoic breath and it's a practice of
Stoicism through breath work and it's a
it's a great way to actually ties into a
lot was what we were just talking about
now about
departing from the real world which is
all a big distraction and going into the
weird a little bit for some
self-reflection in that breath practice
so it's just a breath practice to get
you into a very very deep state of
meditation but being aware of yourself
enough while you're in there to find out
what's going on on the inside
and really observe yourself outside of
the distractions or the real world so
yeah that's me Saturday at 10:00 and
it's a beautiful way to start your
Saturday and then just an event that got
posted James cars'
from finite infinite games is coming to
the store next week I'm just I'm just so
like stoked about this one that's that
playing the infinite game during the
meta-crisis that's june 17th at 3:00
p.m. Eastern Time you can go on the
store website and RSVP there and the
snow is based off a gift economy I'm
viewing it as a gift for all of us to
freely use in this time of need if
you're inspired to give a gift to the
store that you can go to the website I
actually can go to we have a gift
economy website you can give a gift
directly to the store or to any of the
facilitators that just talked or at the
store
stopping said thank you so much everyone
for coming up today
Thanks